CURRICULUM VITAE

Michael L. Treglia, Ph.D.

Postdoctoral Research Associate Department of Biological Science University of Tulsa Oliphant Hall, 304 800 S. Tucker Dr., Tulsa, OK 74105

Phone: +1-918-631-3465 E-mail: mike-treglia@tamu.edu Website: http://mltconsecol.github.io/

Morreale, Cornell University.

Research Interests

My research is focused on identifying conservation strategies for endangered species while advancing analytical techniques and our understanding of ecology. I integrate methods from statistics, GIS, and remote sensing to study landscape-scale patterns and processes, often learning new skills and working with collaborators. My research has largely focused on herpetofauna, though I am interested in extending my work to other taxa and entire ecosystems.

Education

2014-Pres

2006

2009-2014.	Ph.D., Dept. of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.
2007-2010	M.S., Dept. of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.
2004-2007	B.S., Natural Resources, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY.

Research Experience

	life-history traits for amphibians may influence effects of climate change. Supervisor: Dr. Ron Bonett, University of Tulsa
2009-2014	Dissertation. Title: <i>Conservation of the endangered Arroyo Toad across multiple scales.</i> Five chapters focused on identifying threats to, and conservation opportunities for, the Arroyo Toad (<i>Anaxyrus californicus</i>). Supervisor: Dr. Lee Fitzgerald, Texas A&M University.
2007-10	Master's Thesis. Title: A translocated population of the St. Croix Ground Lizard: Analyzing its detection probability and investigating its impacts on the local prey base. Four chapters focused on understanding the ecology of the endangered St. Croix Ground Lizard (Ameiva polops), and examining effects of the species' detectability on monitoring. Supervisor: Dr. Lee Fitzgerald, Texas A&M University.
2007	Research Assistant. Collected field data for a long-term study on relationships between

Postdoctoral Research Associate. Focused on understanding how plasticity and variability of

2005-07 **Research Assistant.** Maintained collection of live reptiles for research and teaching, including over 40 venomous snakes and lizards. Supervisor: Dr. Harry Greene, Cornell University.

forestry management, coarse woody debris, and biodiversity. Supervisor: Dr. Stephen

NSF-REU Intern. Conducted undergraduate research on reptiles and amphibians of St. Vincent, Lesser Antilles, resulting in four publications. Supervisor: Dr. Robert Powell, Avila University.

- 2004-05 **Lab Assistant.** Set up soil samples for chemical analysis with gas chromatograph. Supervisor: Dr. Joseph Yavitt, Cornell University.
- 2003-04 **Intern**. Bred poison dart frogs and analyzed effects of different diets on growth and development rates of the tadpoles. This research was submitted to Intel Science Talent Search Competition. Supervisor: Ms. Cathy Eser, Staten Island Zoo.
- 2002-04 **Intern.** Collected field data on pond turtles in New York for long-term research projects. Supervisor: Mr. David Karrmann, American Museum of Natural History.

Fellowships, Grants, and Awards

- 2013-14 Tom Slick Doctoral Dissertation Fellowship. College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Texas A&M University. \$25,000.
- Willie May Harris Fellowship for Outstanding Teaching Assistants, College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Texas A&M University. \$12,000.
 E. E. Williams Research Grant, The Herpetologists' League. \$1,000.

E. E. Williams Research Grant, The Herpetologists League. \$1,000.

Sylvia Scholarship, Mensa Foundation. \$600.

- 2012, 2013 Travel Grants, Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Program at Texas A&M. \$675; \$700.
- 2010-12 NSF-IGERT Traineeship for the Applied Biodiversity Science Doctoral Program at Texas A&M University. \$84,000.
- Outstanding Master's Student, Department of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas A&M University.
- 2008 2nd Place for Talk, "An Invasive Anole, *Anolis sagrei*, on St. Vincent and its Potential Impact on Native Anoles." Student Research Week, Texas A&M University.
- 2007-08 Regents Graduate Fellowship, Texas A&M University. \$15,000.

2007 Ullman Scholarship, Cornell University. \$500.

2005 Arthur H. and Karin A. Nelson Scholarship, Cornell University. \$500.

Publications (In Review and In Prep. Manuscripts are available upon request)

- In Revision Fitzgerald, L.A., **M.L. Tregli**a, N. Angeli, T.J. Hibbitts, D.J. Leavitt, A.L. Subalusky, I. Lundgren, and Z. Hillis-Starr. Determinants of successful establishment of a new population of the critically endangered St. Croix Ground Lizard (Teiidae: *Ameiva polops*). In Revision for *Restoration Ecology.*
- In Review **Treglia, M.L.**, R.N. Fisher, and L.A. Fitzgerald. Integrating potential and current species distribution models to identify conservation opportunities for an endangered toad. Submitted to *Biological Conservation*.
- In Review Wang, H.H., C.L. Wonka, **M.L. Treglia**, W.E. Grant, F.E. Smeins, W.E. Rogers. Species distribution modeling of an endangered endemic orchid, *Spiranthes parksii* (Correll). Submitted to *AoB Plants*.

Treglia, M.L. and L. A. Fitzgerald. Pitfalls of population estimation: understanding effects of activity on availability bias and population estimates using a field study and a simulation model. Submitted to *Wildlife Research*.

Treglia, M.L., J. Valiulis, D. J. Leavitt, and L.A. Fitzgerald. 2013. Establishment of the Puerto Rican Ground Lizard (*Ameiva exsul*: Teiidae), on St. Croix, U.S. Virgin Islands: a threat to native fauna. *Caribbean Journal of Science* 47(2-3): 373-378.

- Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. 2011. Translocation of the St. Croix ground lizard to Buck Island Reef National Monument, St. Croix, U.S. Virgin Islands. Pp. 109-115. In. Soorae P.S. (ed.) (2011). Global Re-introduction Perspectives: 2011. More case studies from around the globe. Gland, Switzerland: IUCN/SSC Re-introduction Specialist Group and Abu Dhabi, UAE: Environment Agency-Abu Dhabi. Xiv +250 pp.
- **Treglia, M.L.**, O. Ramirez. 2009. *Nerodia rhombifer*. Geographic distribution. *Herpetological Review* 40(2):238.
- Treglia, M.L., A.J. Muensch, R. Powell, and J.S. Parmerlee, Jr. 2008. An invasive anole, *Anolis sagrei* on St. Vincent and its potential impact on native anoles. *Caribbean Journal of Science* 44(2):251–256.
 - Henderson, R.W., **M.L. Treglia**, and S.D. Powell. 2008. *Corallus cookii*. Foraging. *Herpetological Review* 38(4):466.
- Powell, S.D., **M.L. Treglia**, R.W. Henderson, and R. Powell. 2007. Treeboas in the West Indies: responses of *Corallus cookii* and *C. grenadensis* to disturbed habitats. Pp. 374–387 in: R. W. Henderson and R. Powell (eds.). *Biology of the Boas and Pythons*. Eagle Mountain Publ., Utah.
- Treglia, M.L. 2006. An annotated checklist of the amphibians and reptiles of St. Vincent, West Indies. *Iguana* 13: 252–263.
- In Prep. **Treglia, M.L.** and L.A. Fitzgerald. A field experiment on the effects of an active-foraging lizard on its invertebrate prey base. Target Journal *Journal of Zoology*.

Technical Reports

- Treglia, M.L. 2014. Results of surveys for the endangered Arroyo Toad (*Anaxyrus californicus*) in 2013. Annual Report to the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and California Department of Fish and Wildlife.
- Treglia, M. L. and L. A. Fitzgerald. 2010 The translocation of the St. Croix ground lizard, Ameiva polops, to Buck Island Reef National Monument. Final Report to the National Park Service, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and Virgin Islands Department of Planning and Natural Resources.
 - **Treglia, M. L.** and L. A. Fitzgerald. 2010 Population estimation of the St. Croix ground lizard, *Ameiva polops*, on Protestant Cay and Ruth Cay, St. Croix, United States Virgin Islands. Final Report to the United States Fish and Wildlife Service (Cooperative Agreement 401917J125).

<u>**Oral Presentations**</u> (* indicates Invited Presentation)

- Treglia, M.L. and G.T. Kyle. 18-14 May 2014. Estimating effects of land cover at multiple scales on habitat for the endangered arroyo toad. In J. Franklin, J.M. Sierra-Diaz, and L. Sweet (Chairs), *Impacts of Global Change: Linking Across Scales*. Symposium presented at the Annual Meeting of the U.S. Regional Association of the International Association for Landscape Ecology, Anchorage, AK.
- Treglia, M.L. and R.N. Fisher. Integrating Historic and Current Distribution Models of an Endangered Species to Benefit Conservation. *Annual Meeting of the U.S. Regional Association of the International Association for Landscape Ecology, Austin, TX.*
 - *Treglia, M.L. Conservation of the Endangered St. Croix Ground Lizard. *Lecture to Aggies for the Protection of Endangered Species at Texas A&M University.*
- *Treglia, M.L. Manifold GIS: Exploring the Capabilities of an Alternative GIS Package. *U.S. Geological Survey, Western Ecological Research Center San Diego Field Station. San Diego, CA.*

Treglia, M.L. Anthropogenic Disturbances and Conservation of Endangered Amphibians in a Semi-arid Landscape: A Proposal Talk. 12th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.

- Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. Effects of an Insular Lizard Translocation on the Local Invertebrate Assemblage. *Annual Meeting of the Ecological Society of America, Pittsburgh, PA.* Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. Impacts of a Translocated Lizard on an Island Arthropod
 - Assemblage. 11th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.
- Treglia, M.L. and L.A. Fitzgerald. Effects of Detectability on Lizard Population Estimates.

 Annual Meeting of the Southwestern Association of Naturalists, Monterrey, Nuevo Leon, MX.
- Treglia, M.L. The Translocation of an Extirpated Lizard in the Caribbean: A Proposal Talk. Student Research Week/9th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.

 Treglia, M.L., A.J. Muensch, R. Powell, J.S. Parmerlee, Jr. An Invasive Anole: Anolis sagrei on St. Vincent and its Potential Impact on Native Anoles. Student Research Week/9th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.

Poster Presentations

- Treglia, M.L. and A.C. Landon. Integrative Research for Biodiversity Conservation and Water Resource Management. *Student Conference on Conservation Science New York. New York, NY.*
 - **Treglia, M.L.** and R.N. Fisher. Presence-Only Modeling to Understand the Historic Distribution of an Endangered Toad. *7th World Congress of Herpetology. Vancouver, BC, Canada*
- Treglia, M.L. Conserving an Endangered Toad in a Dynamic Landscape. 1st Annual NSF-IGERT Online Competition. Available online at: http://www.igert.org/posters2011/posters/94
- Treglia, M.L. Effects of Detectability on Population Estimates of the Ground-Dwelling Lizard, Ameiva polops. 10th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.

Service

- Reviewer for E.E. Williams Research Grant Program, The Herpetologists' League.
- 2011-12 Co-Chair of the 13th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University.
- 2010-11 Treasurer of the Association of Graduate Wildlife and Fisheries Scientists.
- 2009-10 President of the Association of Graduate Wildlife and Fisheries Scientists.
 - Web-Designer for the 11th Annual Ecological Integration Symposium, Texas A&M University. Judge for Student Research Week, Texas A&M University.
- 2007-08 Mentor for Undergraduate Research Group at Texas A&M University, supervised by Dr. Lee Fitzgerald.
- 2006-07 Co-President of the Cornell Herpetological Society.
- 2005-06 Treasurer of the Cornell Herpetological Society.
- 2004-06 Docent at Staten Island Zoo.
- Reviewer for the following journals: Ecological Modeling (2013); Herpetologica (2013); Herpetological Conservation and Biology (2013); Journal of Applied Ecology (2012-2013); Herpetological Review (2012-2013); Biological Invasions (2012); Journal of Biogeography (2008); Applied Herpetology (2007).
- **Member of the following organizations:** The Herpetologists' League; Society for the Study of Amphibians and Reptiles; U.S. Regional Association of the International Association for Landscape Ecology.

Teaching Experience

2010. 2013	TA for <i>Herpetology</i> , Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.
,	

Guest Lecturer for class, *Recreation Management of Wildlands*, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.

 $2007, 2012 \quad TA \ for \ \textit{Natural History of the Vertebrates}, Texas \ A\&M \ University, College \ Station, TX.$

TA for *Fundamentals of Ecology Lab*, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.

TA for *Natural History of the Invertebrates*, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX.

References

Dr. Lee Fitzgerald - Chair of Doctoral Committee

Professor and Curator, Biodiversity Research and Teaching Collections

Department of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences

Co-Director Applied Biodiversity Science Doctoral Program

Texas A&M University

Mailing Address: 210 Nagle Hall - MS 2258, College Station, TX 77843-2258

Phone: +1-979-862-7245 E-mail: lfitzgerald@tamu.edu

Dr. Robert Fisher - Collaborator; Member of Doctoral Committee

Research Biologist

Western Ecological Research Center, San Diego Field Station

U. S. Geological Survey

Mailing Address: 4165 Spruance Road - Suite 200, San Diego, CA 92101-0812

Phone: +1-619-225-6422 E-mail: rfisher@usgs.gov

Dr. Inci Guneralp – Instructor for course, *Modeling the Environment*; Member of Doctoral Committee

Assistant Professor

Department of Geography

Texas A&M University

Mailing Address: 803F O&M Building - MS 3147, College Station, Texas 77843-7155

Phone: +1-979-845-7155

E-mail: iguneralp@geos.tamu.edu

Dr. Gerard Kyle - Collaborator; Member of Doctoral Committee

Professor

Department of Recreation, Parks, and Tourism Sciences

Texas A&M University

Mailing Address: 437 AGLS Building - MS 2271, College Station, TX 77843-2271

Phone: +1-979-862-3794 E-mail: gkyle@tamu.edu

Dr. Robert Powell - Mentor for Undergraduate Research

Professor

Department of Biology

Avila University

Mailing Address: 11901 Wornall Rd., Kansas City, MO 64145

Phone: +1-816-501-2440 E-mail: robert.powell@avila.edu

Dr. Hsiao-Hsuan (Rose) Wang - Collaborator

Postdoctoral Research Associate

Department of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences

Texas A&M University

Mailing Address: 210 Nagle Hall - MS 2258, College Station, TX 77843-2258

Phone: +1-979-845-5702 E-mail: hsuan006@neo.tamu.edu